Guide to the James S. Jaffe Collection of Jonathan Williams and The Jargon Society
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James S. Jaffe collection of Jonathan Williams and The Jargon Society
1949-1990
1968-1980
YCAL MSS 332
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.42
(4 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
This collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, galley proofs, and artwork that documents a varied sample of projects undertaken by Jonathan Williams and The Jargon Society, 1949-1990. Correspondence documents associations Williams had with collaborators for projects for The Jargon Society and with other publishers. Correspondents include Dana Winslow Atchley, Thomas A. Clark, Ian Gardner, Michael Loeb, Tom Phillips, U. Grant Roman, David Ruff, Henry Holmes Smith, Jon Edgar Webb, and Henry Weaning. Manuscripts and galley proofs document projects related to Williams. This includes a description of the ceramic art of Arnold Ward written by Williams in 1949, and the graphic design work of Dana Winslow Atchley for Jonathan Williams and Nicholas Dean, Blues & Roots, Rue & Bluets (1971) and a manuscript by Michael McClure for Passage (1957) published by The Jargon Society. Artwork documents illustration material created, used, or considered by Williams in his personal projects or works published by The Jargon Society, as well as works by artists associated with him and the press. Artists include Fielding Dawson, Thomas Reuben George, Barbara Mildred Jones, David Ruff, and Paul Sinodhinos.
Jaffe, James S.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from James S. Jaffe Rare Books on the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James S. Jaffe
James S. Jaffe is a bookseller and a bibliographer of works by Jonathan Williams and material published by The Jargon Society. He wrote and published Jonathan Williams: A Bibliographical Checklist of His Writings, 1950-1988 (Haverford, Pennsylvania: J. S. Jaffe Rare Books, 1989).
Jonathan Williams (1929-2008) and The Jargon Society
Jonathan Chamberlain Williams was a poet, essayist, and photographer, as well as the founder and publisher of The Jargon Society.
Educated at St. Albans School, Princeton University, and Black Mountain College, Williams also studied art and design at the Institute of Design in Chicago. His published books of poetry include An Ear in Bartram's Tree; Selected Poems, 1957-1967 (1969), Blues & Roots, Rue & Bluets: A Garland for the Appalachians (with photography by Nicholas Dean, 1971), The Loco Logodaedalist in Situ: Selected Poems, 1968-70 (1972), and Elite/Elate Poems: Selected Poems, 1971-75 (with photography by Guy Mendes, 1979). His published books of photography include Portrait Photographs (1979) and A Palpable Elysium: Photographs (1997). Williams also served as a contributing editor to the photography journal Aperture.
Since 1951, the same year Williams became a student at Black Mountain College, The Jargon Society has published works of poetry, experimental fiction, photography, and art by innovative authors of the twentieth century. Prominent authors and artists published by The Jargon Society include James Broughton, Basil Bunting, Robert Creeley, Robert Duncan, Lou Harrison, Ronald Johnson, Denise Levertov, Paul Metcalf, Henry Miller, Lorine Niedecker, Charles Olson, Joel Oppenheimer, Kenneth Patchen, and Louis Zukofksy. In his poetry and publishing with The Jargon Society, Williams maintained an association with the Black Mountain Poets.
Thomas Meyer (born 1947), a poet and translator whose works include Uranian Roses (1977), Staves Calends Legends (1979), and Sappho's Raft (1982), was Williams' partner and collaborator with The Jargon Society.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, galley proofs, and artwork collected independently by James S. Jaffe, which documents a varied sample of projects undertaken by Jonathan Williams and The Jargon Society. Overall, the collection provides glimpses into the working habits of Williams and underscores his associations with collaborators, including their conflicts and camaraderie. The collection includes especially rich documentation of William's professional and personal relationship with Thomas A. Clark, a poet and publisher, as demonstrated byhis correspondence to Clark.
Correspondence in the collection documents the associations Williams had with collaborators for projects for The Jargon Society, as well as with other publishers. Correspondents include Dana Winslow Atchley, Thomas A. Clark, Ian Gardner, Michael Loeb, Tom Phillips, U. Grant Roman, David Ruff, Henry Holmes Smith, Jon Edgar Webb, and Henry Weaning. The correspondence also includes related printed material collected by Williams' collaborators.
Manuscripts and galley proofs in the collection document projects related to Williams. This includes a description of the ceramic art of Arnold Ward written by Williams in 1949, and the graphic design work of Dana Winslow Atchley for Jonathan Williams and Nicholas Dean, Blues & Roots, Rue & Bluets: A Garland for the Appalachians (1971). It also includes a manuscript by Michael McClure for his Passage, which The Jargon Society published in 1957.
Artwork in the collection includes illustrations created, used, or considered by Williams in his personal projects or works published by The Jargon Society, as well as other works by artists associated with him and the press. Artists include Fielding Dawson, Thomas Reuben George, Barbara Mildred Jones, David Ruff, and Paul Sinodhinos.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1960-1990. II. Manuscripts and Galley Proofs, 1949-1970. III. Artwork, 1950-1970.
Authors, American; Poets, American; Drawings (visual works); Atchley, Dana; Clark, Thomas A., 1944-; Dawson, Fielding, 1930-2002; Dean, Nicholas; Gardner, Ian, 1944-; George, Thomas, 1918-; Jaffe, James S.; Jones, Barbara, 1912-1978; McClure, Michael, 1932-; Phillips, Tom, 1937-; Roman, U. Grant; Ruff, David; Sinodhinos, Paul; Smith, Henry Holmes; Webb, Jon Edgar; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008 -- Friends and associates; Jargon Society
- Correspondence, 1960-1990; Series I; 19
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of correspondence, some printed material, and occasional manuscripts, collected by Jaffe from authors and artists who collaborated with Williams. Most letters were written by Williams and document joint projects with collaborators. The most substantive material relates to Thomas A. Clark.
  - Atchley, Dana Winslow, 1968-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, mostly from 1968 to 1971, that documents the publication, Six Rusticated, Wall-Eyed Poems (1969) and graphic design work Atchley completed for Jonathan Williams and Nicholas Dean for Blues & Roots, Rue & Bluets: A Garland for the Appalachians (1971). Other correspondents include Dean and Michael A. Loeb, who served as representative for Grossman. It also includes a letter from Atchley to Jaffe about the correspondence.
    Material created by Atchley in the graphic design of Blues & Roots, Rue & Bluets: A Garland for the Appalachians is available in Series II, Manuscripts and Galley Proofs.
  - Clark, Thomas A., 1970-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2-14)
    Correspondence, mostly from 1970 to 1980, documents Clark's projects for The Jargon Society, including Some Particulars (1971); A Still Life, with Ian Gardner (1977), and Ways Through Bracken (1980). Other topics include disagreements between Williams and Ian Hamilton Finlay, as well as his own financial and personal tribulations.
    Manuscripts and publications intermingled throughout the correspondence include a typed manuscript by Williams for a poem, "A Wee Tot for Catullus;" a memorial essay written by Williams for his father, Thomas Benjamin Williams (1898-1974); copies of The Jargon Society cards and postcards; and a proof copy of Ways Through Bracken.
  - Gardner, Ian, 1972-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Correspondence that documents Pairidaeza: A Celebration in Lithography & Poetry for the Garden at Levens Hall, Westmoreland (1975). Other topics include shared acquaintances and domestic affairs, as well as the difficult temperament of Ian Hamilton Finlay. The correspondence also includes a single letter to Gardner from Thomas Meyer.
  - Phillips, Tom, 1966-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondence by Williams, mostly from 1969 to 1980, that chiefly documents, Imaginary Postcards (1975). Other correspondence includes letters from Thomas Meyer, a single letter from Phillips to Williams, as well as a letter from Phillips to Jaffe about the correspondence and publications.
    Several publications by The Jargon Society are intermingled throughout the correspondence.
  - Roman, U. Grant, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Correspondence and related material originally compiled by Roman that primarily documents the publishing of Jonathan Williams, Lines About Hills Above Lakes (1964). It documents the planning for the book and Williams' dissatisfaction with the final publication. Includes copies of correspondence between Williams and Henry Wenning, a bookseller in New Haven, Connecticut, who introduced Williams to Roman.
    Related material includes prospectuses for the book, pamphlets about Williams, a printed resume for Williams, and a promotional pamphlet for the Nantahala Foundation.
  - Smith, Henry Holmes, 1967-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Correspondence by Williams that discusses his projects and their shared acquaintances, including Clarence John Laughlin.
  - Webb, Jon Edgar, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    A checklist of Jargon Books (1951-1960) with a letter on typed on it from Williams about Irving Layton, Arnold Ward, and Clarence John Laughlin.
- Manuscripts and Galley Proofs, 1949-1970; Series II; 7
  The series consists of galley proofs and a manuscript for two works by Williams, as well as a typed manuscript for Passage, written by Michael McClure and published by The Jargon Society in 1957.
  - Blues & Roots, Rue & Bluets: A Garland for the Appalachians
    Correspondence about the graphic design is available in Series I, Correspondence.
    - Notes, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Camera-ready copy, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Galley proofs, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Oversize galley proofs, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Photocopies of page proofs, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Notes on Arnold Ward and a Theory of Ceramics, 1949 (Box Bsd)
    Typescript manuscript broadside by Williams, which accompanied an exhibition, "Arnold Ward. Exhibition: Sculpture and Ceramics," at the International Trade Mart in New Orleans, Louisiana in 1951.
  - Passage, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Artwork, 1950-1977; Series III; 11
  The series consists of drawings, collages, engravings, and illustrations by Williams and his collaborators. The works primarily relate to Williams and The Jargon Society.
  - Dawson, Fielding
    - Ink portraits of Jonathan Williams, 1975; 3 drawings, 30.5 x 22.7 cm (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Collages, 1975; 3 collages (Box 4, Folder 27-29)
      Collages created by Dawson for Lyle Bongé, Fielding Dawson, Fielding Dawson, and Jonathan Williams, Hot What?: Collages, Texts, Photographs (1975).
  - George, Thomas Reuben
    - Drawing of trees, 1963; 1 drawing, 21.2 x 35.7 cm on mount 25.8 x 45.7 cm (Box 4, Folder 30)
      Ink drawing intended as an illustration for Ronald Johnson and Thomas George, A Line of Poetry, a Row of Trees, (1964), but it did not appear in the final work.
  - Jones, Barbara Mildred
    - Book cover illustration, 1977; 1 drawing, 23.7 x 15.2 cm (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Pen and colored marker drawing of a scale for the cover of Jonathan Williams and Barbara Mildred Jones, Super-Duper Zuppa Inglese (and Other Trifles from the Land of Stodge) (1977).
  - Ruff, David
    - Engravings, "The Love of the Gentle Land" and "The Light in the Wood", 1951; 2 engravings, each 10.1 x 14.8 cm, on paper 27.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 2, Folder 32)
      The engravings originally accompanied the fifth issue of Inferno (San Francisco, California).
  - Sinodhinos, Paul
    - Book cover illustration, 1975; 1 drawing, 41.8 x 29.8 cm (Box 4, Folder 33)
      Pencil drawing of three figures and six animals for the cover of Thomas Meyer and Paul Sinodhinos, The Umbrella of Aesculapius: Poems (1975).
  - Williams, Jonathan
    - Etching, "Spring Rounds", 1950; 1 etching print, 17.8 x 12.2 cm on paper 22.9 x 17.8 cm (Box 2, Folder 34)
      A proof signed by Williams for his friend, Stanley Willis, a classmate and later English teacher at St. Albans School.
    - Calligraphy, circa 1953; 1 print, 32.2 x 38.2 cm (Box 4, Folder 35)
      Original calligraphy signed by Williams for the book cover of Charles Olson, The Maximus Poems 1-10, (1953).
    - Envelope, circa 1953 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      Large envelope with a printed return address for Williams and abbreviations representing the 5th General Hospital in Stuttgart, Germany, probably used by Williams while he served as a conscientious objector in the United States Army.